Guide to the Kathleen Thompson Norris and Charles Gilman Norris Papers, 1922-1945
Department of Special Collections
Kathleen Thompson Norris and Charles Gilman Norris Papers,
1922-1945
Special Collections M0050
Norris, Kathleen Thompson, 1880-1966.; Norris, Charles Gilman, 1881-1945.
12 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Kathleen Norris, 1954 and 1963, and purchases, 1982, 1983, and 1986.
Biography
Charles Gilman Norris, born 23 April 1881 in Chicago, Illinois, was an American novelist. Norris worked for several magazines before publishing his first novel in 1915. He wrote primarily novels, but also three poetic dramas. He died in 1945. Kathleen Thompson Norris, born 16 July 1880, was an American novelist. She worked for several San Francisco newspapers before marrying Charles Norris in 1909 and moving to New York. She wrote primarily novels, but also short stories and one play.
Scope and Content
Contains manuscripts and correspondence of Kathleen Thompson Norris and Charles Gilman Norris. Also includes photographs and articles about the two authors.
Access Terms
Norris, Charles Gilman, 1881-1945.; Norris, Kathleen Thompson, 1880-1966.; Wilbur, Ray Lyman, 1875-1949.; American literature--20th century.; Authors, American.; Manuscripts (for publication)
Container List
- Series 1: Manuscripts of Kathleen Norris
  - The American Flaggs, Revised mss. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The American Flaggs, Original mss. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The American Flaggs, Original mss. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - An Apple for Eve, Original mss. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - April Escapade, Original mss. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Barberry Bush, Original mss. (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Beauty and the Beast, Carbon (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Beauty's Daughter, Original as appeared in American Magazine (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Beauty's Daughter, Revised copy with ink corrections (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Beauty's Daughter, Revised copy with no corrections (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Beauty's Progress, Corrected copy (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - The Black Flemings, Handwritten original, typescript with corrections, and a clean carbon (Box 4, Folder 13-17)
  - Bakersfield mss. (Box 5, Folder 18)
    Folder of mss. possibly for use as background material for the novel Bread into Roses
  - Bread into Roses, Original mss. (Box 5, Folder 19-20)
  - Burned Fingers, Mss. in notebooks (Box 5, Folder 20a-21)
  - Butterfly, Original mss. (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Cat's Cradle, Original mss. in notebook with carbon of corrected copy. (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Certain People of Importance, Rewritten parts in notebook. (Box 6, Folder 24-27)
  - Certain People of Importance, Carbon (Box 7, Folder 28-30)
  - Corner of Heaven, Original mss. in notebooks. (Box 7, Folder 31-32)
  - Dina Cashman, Original mss. (Box 8, Folder 33-34)
  - The Dreadful Night, Carbon (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Girl Alive, Original mss. (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Heartbroken Melody, Original revised mss. for book publication (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Hildegarde, Original mss. (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Hildegarde, Original mss. (Box 9, Folder 39)
  - Irish Eyes, Corrected mss. (Box 9, Folder 40)
  - Lost Sunrise, Original mss. as it appeared in Colliers and a carbon (Box 9, Folder 41-42)
  - The Love of Julia Borel, Original mss. (Box 10, Folder 43)
  - Lucretia Lombard, Original mss. and a carbon (Box 10, Folder 44-45)
  - Lover's Lane, Original mss. (Box 10, Folder 46)
    First called the Reckless Lovers
  - The Lucky Lawrences, Original mss. (Box 11, Folder 47-48)
  - The Secret of Margaret Yorke., Original and carbon (Box 11, Folder 49-50)
  - Mink Coat, Revised mss. and a portion of a carbon (Box 12, Folder 51-52)
  - Miss Harriet Townshend, Original mss. in a notebook (Box 12, Folder 53)
  - Mystery House, Original mss. (Box 12, Folder 54)
  - Native Born. (Little Ships?), Original mss. (Box 13, Folder 55-56)
  - Now and Again, Original mss. (Box 13, Folder 57-58)
  - Rose of the World, Original mss. (Box 14, Folder 61-62)
  - The Runaway, Original mss. (Box 14, Folder 63)
  - The Sea Gull, Original mss. (Box 14, Folder 64)
  - Second Hand Wife, Master copy and original mss. (Box 15, Folder 65-66)
  - The Secret of the Marshbanks, Original mss. (Box 15, Folder 67-68)
  - Shining Windows, Carbon copy and revised transcript by Kaufman. (Box 15, Folder 69)
  - The Shotwell Street House, Original mss. (Box 16, Folder 70-71)
  - Storm House, Original mss. (Box 16, Folder 72-73)
  - Three Men and Diane, Original mss. (Box 16, Folder 74)
  - Today's Daughter, Revised original mss. (Box 17, Folder 75)
  - Treehaven. Serialized as BLIND YOUTH., Original mss. and a carbon entitled LIND YOUTH. (Box 17, Folder 76-77)
  - Walls of Gold, Carbon (Box 17, Folder 78)
  - When the Past Speaks, Notebooks of the mss. (Box 18, Folder 79-80)
  - Wife for Sale, Original as it appeared in Colliers and a carbon. (Box 18, Folder 81-82)
  - Women in Love, Original mss. (Box 18, Folder 83)
  - The World is Like That., Original mss. and carbon. (Box 19, Folder 84-87)
  - You Can't Have Everything, Original mss. (Box 19, Folder 88)
  - Young Mother Hubbard, Original mss. and galley from Good Housekeeping. (Box 19, Folder 89-90)
  - Big Moment (Box 20, Folder 91)
  - Buttered Beets (Box 20, Folder 92)
  - Come Back to Me Beloved (Box 20, Folder 93)
  - Drama in Everyday Life (Box 20, Folder 94)
  - Enter Private O'Keefe (Box 20, Folder 95)
  - Fascination Fledgerby (Box 20, Folder 96)
  - The Gay Deceivers (Box 20, Folder 97)
  - The Hand of God (Box 20, Folder 98)
  - The Heart of a Mouse (Box 20, Folder 99)
  - Home to Good News (Box 20, Folder 100)
  - In the Back Way (Box 20, Folder 101)
  - Just As If Nothing Had Happened (Box 20, Folder 102)
  - The Murphys of Mayo (Box 20, Folder 103)
  - No Place for a Lady. Who Says So? (Box 20, Folder 104)
  - Pack of Cards (Box 20, Folder 105)
  - Pan's Wife (Box 21, Folder 106)
  - Parley Voo, Marie? (Box 21, Folder 107)
  - Perfect Service (Box 21, Folder 108)
  - Prisoner's Base (Box 21, Folder 109)
  - Pumpkin Coach (Box 21, Folder 110)
  - Runty McCabe Calls (Box 21, Folder 111)
  - Saloons and Women (Box 21, Folder 112)
  - Second Choice (Box 21, Folder 113)
  - Star-Spangled Christmas (Box 21, Folder 114)
  - They Won't Wait (Box 21, Folder 115)
  - Thin Ice (Box 21, Folder 116)
  - This is My Faith (Box 21, Folder 117)
  - T'Was the Night Before Christmas (Box 21, Folder 118)
  - The Unforgivable Sin (Box 21, Folder 119)
  - Yesterday (Box 21, Folder 120)
- Series 2: Manuscripts of Charles G. Norris
  - Brick Without Straw, Handwritten mss. (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
  - The Crackle-Ware Jar, Original mss. (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Flint, Original mss. (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Hands, Original mss. (Box 22, Folder 5-7)
- Series 3: Correspondence
  - Charles G. Norris. TLS & cvr to Mrs. Sloss, 1929 Aug. 20 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Charles G. Norris. TLS & cvr to Mrs. Sloss re: Seed, 1930 Aug. 6 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Charles G. Norris. TLS to Mrs. Sloss, 1934 May 1 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Charles G. Norris. TLS to Nathan Van Patten re: Frank Norris & ms., 1941 Aug. 22 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Kathleen Norris. TLS to [R.L.] Wilbur, 1937 Feb. (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Kathleen Norris. ALS & cvr to Mrs. Sloss, 1943 Dec. [12] (Box 22, Folder 8)
Related Materials
See also the Felton Vertical File on Kathleen Norris, which contains:
(1) obituaries of Kathleen Norris
(2) Book News Monthly reprint: "Kathleen Norris: the Story of the Career of a Woman Novelist of Rare Charm and Power" by Alice Faith Powell
(3) Confidential copy of a copyrighted article Tripe by John Riddell which satirises the Norrises and "Literary Contraception"